back in the decade of the 60s the uh the
famous Theologian Carl Bart
once gave a whole Year's worth of
lectures on the Theology of the 19th
century liberal Theologian Frederick
schlarmacher
and in order to enhance his lectures
Bart brought into the classroom in Basel
a bust of Frederick schlemacher and
throughout the course of the years he
was lecturing on Sly marker and been
critical in his analysis of slammaker he
would direct his remarks to that bus
that was there on the on the podium and
the I was told by students who attended
that particular lecture series that on
the last day of class when he was all
finished with his critique of
sliremacher Bart walked over to the bus
and said well so much for the Theology
of Sly marker and took his hand and
knocked the uh knocked the bust on the
floor and broke it into a hundred pieces
I'm not going to do that with my bust of
Plato because I don't I can't afford to
buy a new one but I would like to pose a
question to you Mr Plato you're telling
us about all these ideas that have
perfect being and are not in a state of
becoming and and the things in this
world are simply imperfect receptacles
what I want to ask you
is how do you know that
and what kind of a question is that
Plato how do you know
well when we look at the history of
philosophy we see that philosophers are
concerned with many different areas of
of uh of Truth
and and in Antiquity the primary focus
of the philosophers was on the level or
in the realm of metaphysics and I've
already defined that as the the realm
above and beyond the Physical Realm they
were interested in what might also be
called as another name for this ontology
that is the science of being what is the
real essence or substance or stuff of
reality what is its being that's the
metaphysical quest in the history of
philosophy
but a second major concern for
philosophers historically and also in
the ancient world
was the subdivision of philosophy that
we call epistemology
and epistemology deals with the science
of learning
and it seeks to answer the question how
do we know what we know
do we know things strictly through
having a sensory experience of them by
seeing feeling tasting touching hearing
and so on
or is the primary way we get it truth
through the formal
actions of deduction and Logic the use
of our mind
or is it a combination of those two
things or is it something else
altogether like flashes of Intuition or
mystical apprehension those are
questions of epistemology how do we know
what we know
well Plato is important not only for
giving to the world his theory of ideas
but also
for expounding another theory that is
identified with him called the theory of
recollection the theory of recollection
now to understand that we have to step
back a little bit
remember where we were in our last
session with his idea of ultimate ideas
and imperfect copies in this world
since everything that we encounter in
this world is only an imperfect copy
of the real ideal or the ideal real
then if we're really going to understand
truth we have to get Beyond
the realm of personal experience of
Senses of what we see and perceive we've
got to get Beyond physical things to get
to that ultimate realm of ideas
a player made an important distinction a
distinction between
opinion
and knowledge
and what he was searching for
was knowledge no it is one of just
canvas people's opinions and hear what
everybody thought about this or thought
about that he wanted to get to real
sound solid knowledge that you could
take to the bank
perhaps his most famous illustration
is the illustration of the parable he
tells about the cave you've all heard of
Plato's Cave
to restate it quickly in an abbreviated
form he tells the stories some prisoners
who from birth are chained inside a cave
and they are facing a wall
and there is a partition behind them
and then behind the partition is the
entrance to the cave where some light
from the sun comes in
and it bounces over this partition and
so on and
casts Shadows
on the wall
now the way the prisoners are situated
in their chains
is that the only thing they can see in
this dimly lit cave
are the Shadows dancing on the wall
they can't see each other they only see
the shadows of each other
and from their limited perspective
their whole
appropriation and apprehension of
reality
is limited to the Shadows on the wall
but what Plato is trying to say is the
Shadows are not real I mean they're real
Shadows
but they only are illusory images of the
reality that is that they're reflecting
on the wall
in order to have true knowledge one has
to get out of the chains and out of the
cave and out into the light
where they can now see things as they
are now remember this is an illustration
because he does not believe that people
who get out of the cave and look in
light of the Sun and look at objects
have therefore entered into the realm of
the ideal now he's using an Earthly
analogy to talk about this spiritual
concept of knowing
Eternal ideas
now in order to get in touch
with the eternal
what is required much more than the
senses
is the use of the Mind
because for Plato the mind is
interrelated with what we would call
the soul
and Plato who had been influenced by the
pythagoreans
believed that every human being has
within his or her body
an eternal soul
that soul the soul of the person
has always been it is eternal
and it is from the realm of the forms or
of the ideas
and that Eternal Soul that is in your
body
has inside of itself already
all the knowledge that there is
in the Eternal Realm
so that when you are born
you are born with the knowledge of the
Eternal
the knowledge of these ideas
already contained in your soul or in
your mind
now that may seem strange to us but
that's very important in the history of
philosophy because Plato is talking
about we call what we call Innate ideas
we are born with ideas that are inherent
within the human mind they're not
learned they're not acquired
they are innate
you're born with
now a technical way to describe that in
philosophy and if you ever do study
philosophy to any degree you're going to
come across this term again and again
and again so we might as well learn it
it's the word a prioritize
knowledge that we are born with
knowledge that is already contained in
the mind
is called a priori knowledge
which means literally knowledge that is
prior to experience
knowledge that you gain from experience
knowledge that you learn through
observation and experimentation and
through experiences of life you call a
posteriori that is knowledge that comes
after uh experience but Opry or our
knowledge is knowledge that's built in
inherent it's it's uh innate
now
for example how do you know that two and
two are four
is that a mental
a knowledge that you have forever
or is that something gained from
experience that's an ongoing debate
among philosophers and students of
epistemology does Christianity believe
that you have built-in knowledge of
anything yes the Apostle Paul tells us
that we are born with a sense of God
that we have built into our minds a
conscience God has written his law on
our hearts and before we ever study
anything we already have a sense of what
is right and what is wrong built in to
our souls as it were
so the idea of our priori knowledge is
not found simply in Plato in fact the
whole history of what we call
rationalism on one side of the
philosophical scale
has some form of a priori knowledge or
other which we will see as we go along
but I'm just introducing these Concepts
to you at this point in our historical
survey
now Plato's view
as I said was heavily influenced by
Pythagoras
and Pythagoras and the pythagoreans
taught a Doctrine
that was called the doctrine of the
transmigration of the Soul
transmigration now that's a fancy word
trans migration
now there's nothing in that word that
you haven't heard many many many times
you've heard the prefix trans
transoceanic Trans American
trans World Airlines TWA trans means
across
okay
if you transport it you take it across
from one gate to another and so on and
you've all heard the word migration
there's emigration immigration migrator
migratory birds birds that migrate are
birds that move from one location to
another
so transmigration just simply means
moving or migrating across from one
something to another something
well the concept of transmigration of
the soul that was developed by the
thygerians
you've heard of
Only You Hear It by a different term
the term you usually associate with this
idea is the idea of re-incarnation very
important to Eastern philosophy and
Eastern religion that says that the
souls of people
go through many different
incarnations
that is to be incarnate means to be in a
body
in the flesh
and so when you were born you were born
with a soul and a body now Christianity
believes
if that only happens once and then the
Judgment you're born you live you die
you're judged and so on
but Eastern religions that hold the
reincarnation say you may be born and in
this life and you may have Brady Murphy
experience this under hypnosis and
recall that you were the Prince of Wales
back in the 16th century or something
that you've lived 27 times in the past
either as a human being or as some
animal
some people have views that they want to
make sure that they protect the lives of
animals because they believe that some
people
when they die
are reincarnated
as animals depending on how you lived in
this world the idea being that if you
live a virtuous life in this world in
your next Incarnation you'll have a
better deal you'll get a higher state or
if you've led a bad life in this world
in your next Incarnation you'll have a
lower state of existence and so on but
the basic principle is that the soul
keeps moving from one body to the next
or from one place to the next
now Plato believed in a form of
reincarnation
which he borrowed from the pythagoreans
and so he would say that the soul
however does not start when you were
born the soul is eternal
and when the soul is born into this
particular Incarnation it brings all
this knowledge that of the Eternal Realm
however once the body
captures a soul
the impact of the body on the soul
is to dull and obscure and hold down the
clarity of vision
that would be found in a pure Soul or
pure mind
that's why Plato would speak of
the body being the prison House of the
Soul
now again think about how we learn we
learn by with our eyes our ears our
hands and so on as well as with the
thoughts of our mind
now in our day we put most of the uh
emphasis in the scientific realm in our
ability to learn with the senses
empirically as it were
if you can't see a taste it touch it or
smell you know it doesn't exist or it's
suspect
Plato is just the opposite
Plato believed that the highest way to
know anything is through the mind not
through the senses because the senses
are always distorting reality and even
if the senses have a perfect grasp of
the reality that they are seeing out
there remember that that reality that
they're saying the physical world is it
best an imperfect copy of the idea
so that you can't get any further than
the Shadows on the wall in the cave
through what we would call the
scientific investigation
in order to get real truth you got to
get in touch with the rational because
the rational perceives the real now
if these perfect ideas that are stored
up in your soul and in your mind are
being suppressed or hindered or obscured
by the impact of the weakness of your
flesh and the weakness of your body how
do you get at it
well again you get at it through recall
through recollection
through remembering
and how do you get to that remembrance
back to the Socratic method
by questioning by contemplating by
reasoning by dialogue and debate we try
to cut through the prison bars of the
body to get down to the to the the
rudimentary ideas that are long buried
in the soul
and that's the process of Education the
process of education is not to give you
information you don't already have
but it is to get out of you the
information that's already there
see the difference
now in order to prove his theory of
recollection
he he wrote several dialogues one of
which was the meno dialogue
m e n o fascinating dialogue I remember
when I used to teach ancient philosophy
in college
that I took a student who had no
background in in math and no background
in philosophy
and got him in front of the class and I
played the role of Plato
in the dialogue and this poor student
unwittingly was performing the role of
the character for whom the dialogue is
named Mina
Amino is a slave boy
who has no education
and in the dialogue Socrates is
cross-examining Mino
and just asks him certain questions
that are not designed to inform the
slave boy of any information just asking
him basic questions
and what he gets out of them out of the
slave boy
after asking the right questions he gets
the slave boy to articulate the
Pythagorean theorem a squared plus b
squared equals c squared he could draw
some diagrams in the sand and all of
that and has the boy do this and the boy
figures it out and comes up with this
classic
theorem of math
and Plato says that by this exercise of
questioning probing dialoguing proves
that the knowledge was already there
innately in the mind
all right now for Plato
one of his concerns with this knowledge
Pursuit
was to do what he called the job of
saving
the phenomena
saving the phenomena
he saw the saving of the phenomena the
chief task of science what does he mean
by saving the phenomena well what what
are the phenomena
the phenomena are the data bits
that we experience
the shadows in the cave the things that
we see in this world trees and plains
and birds and bees and and water and
streams and so on
and the scientist is just like the
ancient philosopher is looking at all of
this and saying how can we make sense
out of it
phenomena happens to refer to that which
is the realm of appearances
we see things as they appear well what
laws or theories will make sense of all
of that stuff that appears to us in our
lifetime
so Plato is saying we need an adequate
system of thought that will save the
phenomena that is make sense out of it
redeem it from chaos
and his philosophical system is not just
abstract philosophy but it's really
trying to give the metaphysical or
philosophical foundation for science
the ultimate theory that will make sense
out of everything that's what he sees as
the task of philosophy and the task of
Science and that's where they marry and
of course the history of science follows
very closely the history of philosophy
and you're all aware of what happens
with the radical changes and upheavals
that take place in the world of science
we talk about Paradigm shifts
where a paradigm is a model
and it's a model that we hope is a model
of reality like Copernicus had like
Ptolemy had like Newton had like
Einstein has
and the purpose of this Paradigm or this
model is to explain everything that we
observe
but the problem is in every system
scientific system that's ever been
devised there have always been what we
call anomalies and what are anomalies
anomalies are those little quirks of our
experience that aren't explained by the
system they don't really fit and you get
enough of these and these things become
bothersome and irksome enough what
happens somebody comes along changes the
Paradigm gives us a new new model that
will then explain these strange things
that didn't fit in the old model and
that's the way science moves and
progresses forward that whole business
that whole task is doing what Plato said
saving the phenomena if you have
phenomena that don't fit into the
current system if you want to save that
phenomenon you've got to expand your
Paradigm and change it finally
Plato taught the ultimate idea
was the idea of the good
the idea of the good
and he defined it this way that the
perfect ideal of good
is the universal author of all things
beautiful
and all things that are right
and it's the source of all reason and
Truth
now there's a great argument in among
historians and philosophers whether
Plato's idea of the good is Plato's God
he doesn't say that it is but one of the
reasons why it's so tempting to see it
is because it looks so similar to the
biblical concept of God who is absolute
perfect
Eternal goodness
who is the author and Fountainhead of
all that is beautiful all that is good
and all that is true is it any Wonder
that apologists such as Justin Martyr
would read the things of Plato and say
so much of Plato's thinking
seems to reflect the influence of the
logos
the Divine logos who enlightens all who
come into the world